<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon of the nature and necessitie of godly feare Preached in the Cathedrall Church of Chester, in September, 1614.</title>
            <author>Case, William, 1584 or 5-1634.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18125</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4766</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118534</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853741</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853741</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19136</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18125)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19136)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1166:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon of the nature and necessitie of godly feare Preached in the Cathedrall Church of Chester, in September, 1614.</title>
                  <author>Case, William, 1584 or 5-1634.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T[homas] S[nodham] for Edmund Weauer, and are to sould at the great south-dore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: William Case.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Fear of God --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19136:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON OF THE NATVRE AND NECESSITIE of <hi>Godly Feare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Preached in the Cathedrall Church of CHESTER, in <hi>September,</hi> 1614.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DEVT. 5.29.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Oh that there were ſuch a heart in my people, that they would feare me, and keepe all my Commandements alwayes, that it might be well with them and their children for euer.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 14.27.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>The Feare of the Lord is a well-ſpring of life to auoid the ſnares of death.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PROV. 14.16.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>A wiſe man feareth, and departeth from euill.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>T. S.</hi> for <hi>Edmund Weauer,</hi> and are to ſould at the great South-dore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:19136:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19136:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT <hi>WORSHIPFVLL</hi> S<hi rend="sup">ir</hi> RANDALL CREVV Knight, <hi>one of his Maieſties Serieants</hi> at the LAVV.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right worſhipfull:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Doe vnfainedly profeſſe my ſelfe for euer bound vnto you, for your vndeſerued goodneſſe towards me, and your forward and willing inclination to entertaine me into your fauour. Which, as it doth require and challenge from mee all reſpectfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement: ſo am I willing to take any occaſion to witneſſe the ſame, and for that cauſe am bold to preſent this ſmall diſcourſe vnto your Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, as a pledge of my vnfained thankeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: humbly deſiring you to yeelde vnto it your fauourable acceptance, vntill ſuch time as
<pb facs="tcp:19136:3"/>heereafter, I ſhall by ſome better meanes giue more pregnant testimony of my thankefull minde and dutifull deuotion. In the meane time I ſhall endeuour myſelfe to deſerue your good fauours, and will not ceaſe to pray that the Almighty God may multiply vpon you and yours all the bleſsings and honours of this life, and after this life crowne you with immortall glory in CHRIST JESVS.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips humbly deuoted in the Lord Ieſus WILLIAM CASE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19136:3"/>
            <head>OF THE NATVRE AND NECESSITIE of Godly Feare.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Pſalm. 4</hi> ver. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Stand in awe, and ſinne not.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HERE is in the Church of God, and euer ſhall be vnto the end of the world, people of a two-fold condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; both prefigured in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of the Old Teſtament, by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny typicall premonſtrations, as of <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar,</hi> of <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael,</hi> of <hi>Iacob</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> of the Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites &amp; the Aegyptians, and the like; and alſo illuſtrated in the new, by many parabolicall reſemblances, by Wheat &amp; Tares, Sheepe &amp; Goates, by Wiſe and Fooliſh Virgins, and diuers ſuch other; ſignifying thereby the continuall op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition betweene the myſticall members of Chriſt, and the powers of the kingdome of Satan; between the God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and the Wicked, the Elect and the Reprobate. Wherof the bleſſed and kingly Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> a glorious type of Chriſt, hauing many times plentifull experience, but more particularly at that inſtant, when he compoſed this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:19136:4"/>of the manifold vexations and grieuances of <hi>Saul</hi> and his adherents: Hee writ this Pſalme, conſiſting partly of deuout petitions vnto God; partly of ſharp reprehenſions vnto his enemies; partly of godly exhortation to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance: and laſtly, of diuine reſolution with himſelfe, Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto God in the firſt verſe, exprobrating his enemies in the ſecond and third, admoniſhing them in the fourth and fift, and in the three laſt verſes, reſoluing with him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, that the light of Gods countenance ſhould miniſter vnto him more cauſe of gladneſſe and reioycing, then all the vaine and vncertaine delights of natures bleſſings, wherein worldly minded men doe chiefly repoſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues can poſſibly afford vnto them; and that in full aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red confidence thereof onely, hee would reſt himſelfe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied and ſecure.</p>
            <p>In imitation whereof, though wee haue begun this morning Sacrifice with Prayer, yet beeing conſcious euery one of our owne guiltineſſe for ſinne, we cannot as the Prophet doth here in the perſon of Chriſt, by way of reproach, ſhew any contempt each of other, and therfore itremaines that wee proceed in the third place,<note place="margin">Heb. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>to exhort one another while it is called to day</hi> (as the Apoſtle ſpeakes:) and that ſo much the rather, becauſe the day draweth neer; that as litterally in this place the wicked enemies of <hi>Dauid,</hi> vnder the conduct of <hi>Saul,</hi> did grieue and perſecute him, as typically the accurſed Iewes, vnder the protection of <hi>Pontius Pilate</hi> did purſue vnto death, and crucifie the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour of the world: ſo ſpiritually, we hauing truely and really, by the aboundance of our ſinnes, vnder the power and ſubiection of Satan, betrayed and diſhonoured our Lord and Redeemer, may aboue all things be carefull that hereafter <hi>we ſtand in awe and ſinne not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words I doe briefly obſerue theſe two ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cialties. Firſt, <hi>the preuention of ſinne.</hi> Secondly, <hi>the prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſinne.</hi> The prouention of ſinne in this word [<hi>ſtand in awe;</hi>] The prohibition of ſinne in this [<hi>ſinne not.</hi>]</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the word (as Interpreters doe tranſlate
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:19136:4"/>it) doth originally ſignifie a ſimple commotion or pertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of the minde of man in generall, without any limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation at all. Now as the minde of man is mooued by di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers and ſundry paſſions; ſo Tranſlators doe diuerſly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine it. Some to anger, as the vulgar hath it <hi>Iraſcimini,</hi> be angry; ſuppoſing that <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the fourth to the Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians, and the 26. verſe, hath reference vnto this Scripture, where he ſaith, <hi>be angry, but ſinne not.</hi> Others limit it to an intention of feare, and ſo render it <hi>contremiſeite,</hi> tremble; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding thereby that ſodaine and diſtracted trembling and amazement, which is the beginning of repentance; ſuch a one as ſurprized <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the way vnto Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,<note place="margin">Acts 9.6.</note> when the light rom Heauen had caſt him down, &amp; he heard the voyce, it is ſaid, that he <hi>trembling and greatly aſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed ſaid, Lord, what wilt thou haue me to doe?</hi> And laſtly, others, but eſpecially our learned Church doe tranſlate it, [<hi>Stand in awe.</hi>] Signifying thereby, not onely that ſodaine horror which ſurprizeth all the powers of the ſoule, when great and vnexpected euills doe preſently aſſault it; but likewiſe a continuall motion of feare in the ſould, whereby it doth alwaies ſtand in awe by the expectancy and danger of euills to come. So including not onely <hi>tremorem,</hi> but <hi>timorem;</hi> not onely a ſodaine paſſion of aſtoniſhment, but alſo a cautelous and deliberate paſſion of doubtfulneſſe and feare. According as the Apoſtle admoniſheth. <hi>Hee that thinketh he ſtandeth, let him take heede,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 11.20.</note> and <hi>be not high minded, but feare.</hi> Intimating that the onely way to be ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure from the danger of puniſhment for ſinne, is to feare to commit ſinne. As if the Prophet ſhould ſay in more words. O yee Sonnes of men, yee mighty and great men of this world, how long will ye hold on by your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and ſcorne to impute that as a reproach and ſhame vnto me, which is my greateſt glory; pleaſing and decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing yourſelues in the lying and deluding vanities of this world? For be ye ſure that although the Lord doe yet ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer you for a time, thus contemptuouſly to reproach the footeſteps of his annointed; yet at length will he returne
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:19136:5"/>and vindicate him that is godly, from the deſpight of his enemies, and ſet him apart for himſelfe; <hi>the Lordwill heare when I call vpon him.</hi> And therefore it is now high time that ye bethinke your ſelues, that your hearts be ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and ſetled in a fearefull and awfull reſpect of that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, which ſurely will be auenged on all his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, vnleſſe the current and ſtreame of your crying ſins be reſtrained by a godly feare. Which is the trueſt expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of this Text, and moſt agreeable to the ſenſe of this Scripture. <hi>Feare</hi> therefore is the duty here ſimply propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>force. Firſt <hi>poſitiuely,</hi> as it is a Diuine iniunction to ſtand in awe and feare of God at all times; and then <hi>relatiuely,</hi> as it is the ſpeciall and onely meanes for the auoyding and reſtrayning of ſinne. In the firſt I will conſider; firſt, what Feare is in it ſelfe, then how God onely is to be feared, and none other beſides him.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>Feare</hi> in it ſelfe is a paſſion of the ſenſible appetite, ſhunning and auoyding irreſiſtable euills, future and to come: For the better vnderſtanding whereof, wee are to conſider, that as there are in man two principall fountains of direction; namely, Reaſon and Senſe; ſo are there like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite. For wee muſt haue ſpeciall care in ſearching out the knowledge of theſe things, that we make a difference betweene the Will properly and ſtrictly taken, and that inferiour naturall deſire which is called the Appetite; the one in diuers reſpects being more excellent then the other: the one is as the Miſtreſſe, the other as the Seruant. For the appetite is the wills ſolicitor, and the will is the appe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for all actions which proceed from the diſpoſition of the will, are in the power thereof eyther to be performed or ſtayed: whereas the appetite cannot chuſe, but riſe at the ſight of ſuch things as it ias affected withall; neyther is it in our power whether wee be ſtirred with afections or no. Finally, the will is a free deſire or bending of our ſoules vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19136:5"/>the hauing or doing of that good, which onely rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and vnderſtanding preſcribeth: the appetite an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt and neceſſary inclination &amp; deſire, vnto that good onely which ſenſe propoſeth. The one is called <hi>appetitus rationalis,</hi> the reaſonable appetite; the other <hi>appetitus ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitivus,</hi> the ſenſible appetite. For the obiect of the will is that good which reaſon doth leade vs to ſeeke, and the obiect of the appetite is whatſoeuer ſenſible good may be wiſhed for. Now as our appetite doth immediately &amp; poſitiuely reſpect and ſeeke after good; ſo doth it neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarily by conſequent auoyd that which is euill; ſo that as poſitiuely good, ſo negatiuely euill, is the obiect thereof. And according vnto the diuers circumſtances of its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect of good and euill, ſo is the appetite varied into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers formes and faſhions, which are called the affections or paſſions of the minde. For as in the generall it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined vnto good, it is called Loue, and as it reſiſteth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, it is called Hatred; as it earneſtly purſueth that which is good, it is called Zeale, and as it vehemently oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that which is euill, it is called Anger; as it is affected with the good which is preſent, it is ſtiled by the name of Ioy: and as it hath reference vnto the preſent euill, it is named Sorrow; if it reſpect future good, Hope; and if future euill, Feare. Feare then is a paſſion or affection of the ſenſible appetite, ſhunning and auoyding euills, fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and to come.</p>
            <p>So that ſeeing what Feare is in it ſelfe, in conſidering in the next place, that this feare is only to be referred vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God; I will reduce my diſcourſe into theſe two heads: firſt, that he is to be feared: and ſecondly, that he onely is to be feared, and no other beſides him.</p>
            <p>For the firſt. It may be a queſtion, in as much as the obiect of feare is euill, (for wee feare not any thing pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly, but as euill,) how can God be ſaid to be feared who is onely good; yea the ſoueraigne good of all? To which I anſwer, that <hi>Feare</hi> hath a double reſpect. Firſt, of the euill it flies from, and ſecondly of the good from
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19136:6"/>whence the euill comes. If it be referred vnto the euill, it feares it <hi>per ſe,</hi> for it ſelfe; if vnto the good, it feares it, but by accident, not for it ſelfe, but <hi>propter aliud,</hi> for that euill it brings with it. So that although the obiect of feare properly be euill; yet by accident and as it were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>directly we may be ſaid to feare that which is good alſo. And that in two reſpects. Firſt, leſt the good which wee loue, may by ſome euill be loſt and taken from vs. And ſecondly, becauſe the good we feare, may haue in it ſome power and ſtrength to inflict euill vpon vs. Which two reſpects (the Philoſophers ſay) are the onely originall cauſes of feare, <hi>Amor</hi> and <hi>Defectus,</hi> Loue and Weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; Loue vnto that good which we feare to looſe; and inability to reſiſt that euill, which would take that good from vs. For why doe we feare death, but becauſe wee loue life? and why doe we feare a good Magiſtrate, but becauſe hee hath that power to inflict puniſhment vpon vs which we are not able to reſiſt? If we did not loue that which is good, we ſhould not feare to loſe it. And if we had power to withſtand that which is euill, we ſhould not feare it at all. For the biting of a dogge is euill, but the Lion feares it not, becauſe he is able to reſiſt it. What was the reaſon that <hi>Saul</hi> feared, and <hi>Dauid</hi> had courage to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter <hi>Goliah?</hi> but becauſe the one both ſaw his forces vnequall, and alſo being deſtitute of Faith, did deſpaire of the Lords aſſiſtance; whereas the other being aſſured by Faith that the Lord would be his helper, feared not. So that loue vnto good, and inability to reſiſt euill being the onely cauſes of feare; in both of theſe reſpects there is none whom wee ought to feare ſo much as God the Lord. For who better to be beloued, <hi>in his preſence being the fulneſſe of ioy, and at his right hand are pleaſures for euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more?</hi> Or who is able to oppoſe his almighty power; and therefore in that reſpect who is more to be feared alſo? In confidence wherof the Prophet reſolueth,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 23.4.</note> that <hi>though he were in the valley of the ſhadow of death, yet would he feare none ill, becauſe the Lord was with him.</hi> According vnto
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19136:6"/>which two, Diuines haue diſtinguiſhed feare to be two-fold; eyther <hi>ſeruilis,</hi> or <hi>filialis,</hi> a ſeruile or a filiall feare. The ſeruile feare doth feare God becauſe hee is iuſt and pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, the filiall feare becauſe hee is good and mercifull: the ſeruile feare doth bridle ſin, the filiall feare doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoke vnto righteouſneſſe; the one doth reſtraine the luſt of the fleſh, the other doth ſet forward the motions of the Spirit. Whiles we haue but the firſt, we are but as ſeruants, but when wee haue the ſecond, we are accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as Sonnes; by the one we are afraid to ſuffer, by the other wee are afraid to offend; the obiect of the one is <hi>malum poenae</hi> the euill of puniſhment; the obiect of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is <hi>malum culpae,</hi> the euill of ſinne; the ſeruile feare proceeds from that which the Apoſtle calls, <hi>ſpiritum Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitutis, the ſpirit of Bondage;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8.15.</note> and the filiall feare from that which hee calls <hi>ſpiritum Adoptionis, the ſpirit of Adoption: For we haue not</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>receiued the ſpirit of Bondage to fear again, but we haue receiued the ſpirit of Adoption, whereby wee cry Abba Father:</hi> Both of them the good worke of Gods moſt holy ſpirit; the filiall feare he worketh onely in his elect children, the ſeruile feare both in the elect and the reprobate; though not vnto the ſame end. But in the reprobate as a pledge and beginning of future and greater puniſhments; and in his elect, as it is an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into grace, whereby the ſeruant of God is admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed to forbeare ſinne, for inaſmuch as a Chriſtian man is an Hypoſtaſis, conſiſting of two natures, which the Scripture notes out by the Fleſh and the Spirit, the Old man and the New, and ſuch like, therfore are both of theſe feares required, the one to reſtraine the power of ſinne, the other to ſet forwards the powers of righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Yet not both in the ſame degree of reſpect. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in a Chriſtian the ſeruile feare cannot be wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting; becauſe that as in a bad way wee haue as much (if not more) neede of a bridle then a ſpurre: ſo wee, as it were riding on through the rough and thorny paths of ſinne, haue in that reſpect more neede of that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19136:7"/>feare to hold vs backe: yet for all that it is not to be para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelld with the filiall feare, nor to be accounted a true and eſſentiall part of Gods worſhip and honour, but onely as a remouer of his diſhonor and a preparatiue vnto the filiall feare. In which reſpect, one of the Fathers com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares ſeruile feare to a Needle, and filiall feare to a Thred, ſo that as the needle doth enter into the cloth not to ſtay there, but to draw in the thred after it; ſo is the ſeruile feare required in euery Chriſtian, not as a thing accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in the ſight of God, but onely as a preparatiue vnto that filiall feare, wherein his true ſeruice doth eſpecially conſiſt.</p>
            <p>From the conſideration of which things, wee may ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this obſeruation, and carefully lay it vp in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mories, as a leſſon neceſſary to be learned of all men; That ſo long as we feare the iudgements of God, wee may deeme our ſelues the ſeruants of God: but wee are neuer the ſonnes of God vntill we feare him for his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. The ſeruant feares his Maſter; but why? becauſe that if hee doe not well hee will puniſh him; but the ſonne feares his Father, becauſe he loues him, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is fearefull to diſpleaſe him; hauing more regard vnto his Fathers griefe, then his owne puniſhment; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecting more the loſſe of his Fathers loue, then the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curring,<note place="margin">Gal. 4.30.</note> and the induring of his owne paine. Now the ſeruant abides not in the houſe for euer, (ſaith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture) but they which haue receiued the adoption of ſonnes ſhall onely inherit. Why? becauſe hee feares not God for God, but onely for himſelfe, which properly is not true feare, becauſe the obiect of it is not truely euill. For <hi>malum poenae,</hi> the euill of puniſhment, which ſeruile feare onely reſpects, is not ſimply euill; not euill, <hi>ſuo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere,</hi> (as the Schooles ſpeak) nor <hi>ſua natura</hi> in it owne na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, (for it is a worke of the pure and exact Iuſtice of God,) but onely <hi>malum ſecundum not,</hi> euill in reſpect of vs: Whereas on the other ſide, the childe-like feare is the onely true feare, becauſe onely its obiect is truely euill.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:19136:7"/>For <hi>malum culpae,</hi> the euill of ſinne, which it chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is <hi>ſua natura,</hi> in it owne nature euill; although our corrupted nature account it as <hi>bonum ſecundum nos,</hi> ſec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming good vnto vs, and therefore doth our inclination ſo much deſire to commit it. And howſoeuer the feare of ſonnes may be ſaid alſo to reſpect <hi>malum poenae,</hi> the euill of puniſhment, yet is it not that puniſhment which the other lookes at; for ſeruile feare lookes onely at that which is called <hi>poenae ſenſus,</hi> that puniſhment which it ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiblie ſhall feele; but the filiall feare at that which is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>poena damni,</hi> the puniſhment of loſſe, fearing more to loſe the loue and fauour of God, and the promiſed ioyes of Heauen: then to be iuſtly puniſhed by God, and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure all the torments of Hell. Let vs therefore conſider, that ſo long as we do feare God onely for his iudgements, we are but ſeruile, the ſeed of the bond-woman; but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we feare him for his goodneſſe, we are not the ſonnes of the free-woman, not the true adopted ſonnes of God: By the one we are ſtill vnder the Law; but by the other, we are vnder Grace: The one is wrought in vs by the threatnings of the Law, the other by the ſweet promiſes of the Goſpell. In ſumme: The true childe of God is more afraide to deſerue puniſhment, then to ſuffer puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Now for the ſecond, that God onely is to be feared, it may be alſo doubted that in as much as the Lord hath commanded vs in his word to feare our <hi>Parents,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Leuit. 19.3. Rom. 13.4.7. Epheſ. 6.5.</note> to feare the <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> the <hi>Gouernours</hi> which hee hath ſet ouer vs: How is he ſaid onely to be feared, and what propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is there between that feare which we owe vnto God, and that which we are to giue vnto men: what difference is there betweene the one and the other? To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that God onely, and no other beſides him, is to be feared in theſe two reſpects and limitations; <hi>Simpliciter,</hi> and <hi>per ſe</hi> ſimply and by himſelfe. For firſt, God alone, and neyther Angell, Deuill, nor any other creature beſides, is to befeared, <hi>ſimpliciter,</hi> ſimply, becauſe he onely
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19136:8"/>hath a ſimple and an abſolute power ouer vs. For, howſoever the creature may haue power to doe that euill which we may feare: yet is not its power abſolute, nor ouer all and euery part of vs, but limited vnto our bodies and goods onely. Whereas Gods power is vnli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited and abſolute, both ouer ſoule and body, goods and all, and is able to deſtroy all. In which reſpect our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Sauiour admoniſheth his Diſciples, <hi>not to feare them which kill the body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 10.28.</note> 
               <hi>but are not able to kill the ſoule: but rather feare him who is able to deſtroy both ſoule and body in hell.</hi> And the reaſon why wee are to feare the Magiſtrate, the Apoſtle giues in the 13. of his Epiſtle to the <hi>Romanes,</hi> becauſe <hi>he heares not the Sword for nought.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.4.</note> But the power of the ſword is limited, eyther to our goods, or bodies, or liues, and cannot extend vnto the ſoule and conſcience: and therefore is hee not to be feared abſolutely as God is, becauſe hee hath not that abſolute power that God hath.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God onely is to be feared <hi>per ſe,</hi> for his owne ſake, for himſelfe, without any reference at all to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other creature. For although both Angells, Men and Diuells haue power in ſome things to hurt vs; yet haue they it not originally from themſelues, nor according to their owne wills, but onely from God, and according to his will: Neyther haue they it alwaies, nor in what mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure it pleaſeth themſelues, but both how much &amp; how long it pleaſeth God: And for that cauſe our Sauiour an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Pilate,</hi> boaſting that he had power eyther to looſe him,<note place="margin">Iohn 10.11.</note> or put him to death: <hi>Thou couldest haue no power at all ouer mee</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>vnleſſe it were giuen thee from aboue.</hi> Yea, the Diuell himſelfe whom the Scripture ſtiles by the name of the Prince of this world, had no power to touch ſo much as any the leaſt thing that was <hi>Iobs,</hi> further then the Lord permitted and gaue leaue. Although there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we are by the precept of Almighty God to feare our Parents and Gouernours, yet are wee not to feare them for themſelues, but as they haue power and commiſſion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19136:8"/>from God,<note place="margin">Rom. 13.1.</note> for <hi>there is no power</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>but of God.</hi> God therefore hauing all power both in himſelfe, and of himſelfe, and vniuerſall and abſolute ouer all, and at all times; is onely ſimply and by himſelfe to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and all other but vnder him, or from him, and as farre as he permits and commands.</p>
            <p>So that as by ſtrong euidence of reaſon, we ſee that it cannot be denied by any man, but that hee is to referre and yeeld all feare onely, and eſpecially vnto God. So alſo doth the conſent of Scripture ſound altogether that way, exacting it as one of the chiefeſt dueties, that a chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian is to performe: namely, at all times to ſtand in awe and continuall feare of the Maieſty of Almighty GOD. <hi>Oh that there were ſuch a hart in my people</hi> (ſaith the Lord,) <hi>that they would feare me, and keepe all my commandements al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, that it might be well with them and their children for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer.</hi> Deut. 5.29. <hi>Thou ſhalt feare the Lord thy God, and him onely ſhalt thou ſerue,</hi> Deutro. 10.20. And in the 12. verſe. <hi>And now O Iſrael! what doth the Lord require of thee, but to feare the Lord thy God, to walke in his waies, &amp;c. I haue gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen you a Land for which you did not labour, and Cities which yee built not, and yee dwell in them, of the Vineyards and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards which ye planted not doe you eate; now therefore feare the Lord,</hi> Ioſu. 24.14. <hi>And I ſay vnto you my friends</hi> (ſaith our bleſſed Sauiour in the 12. of S. <hi>Lukes</hi> Goſpell) <hi>be not afraid of them that kill the body, and after that haue no more that they can doe: But I will forewarne you whom you ſhall feare: Feare him which after he hath killed, hath power to caſt into hell: yea, I ſay vnto you feare him. Feare God and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the King,</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Peter.</hi>) And <hi>Feare God, and giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie vnto him,</hi> ſaith the Angell that had the euerlaſting Goſpell to preach vnto all the earth, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 14.7.</p>
            <p>And the Scriptures doth not only abound in precepts to this effect: but alſo is plentifull in examples hereof. As <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 22.12. <hi>Lay not thy hand</hi> (ſaith the Lord vnto him) <hi>vpon the childe, nor doe him any hurt, for now I know that thou feareſt me, becauſe that for my ſake thou wouldſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:19136:9"/>not haue ſpared thine onely Sonne. Ioſeph</hi> alſo witneſſeth the ſame of himſelfe: <hi>For I feare God,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Gen.</hi> 42.17. The Aegyptian Mid-wiues likewiſe are memorable for their feare of God in the firſt of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and therefore did they dare to breake that barbarous and bloudy com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of King <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> wherby they were appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to kill all the male children of the Hebrewes. <hi>Obadiah.</hi> the Ruler of King <hi>Ahabs</hi> houſhold, in the 1. of the <hi>Kings</hi> 18.3. is ſaid to haue feared God greatly, and therefore did he hide a hundred of the Lords Prophets from the cruelties of <hi>Iezabel. Iob</hi> alſo approued by the mouth of God himſelfe for his feare. Iob. 1.8. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> in the fift Pſalme, <hi>In thy Feare, O Lord, will I euer worſhip to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thy holy Temple.</hi> And in the New Teſtament, <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chary</hi> and <hi>Elizabeth, Simeon, Cornelius, Ananias,</hi> and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others are recorded to their perpetuall praiſe, for their feare of God. Yea, the whole Scripture doth runne throughout, that Gods people haue euer beene a feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full people; that Gods generation is a trembling genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And no maruell. Becauſe they cannot ſerue their God, vnleſſe they doe feare him; feare being the onely and chiefe part of his worſhip. <hi>For the feare of the Lord is the beginning of wiſedome,</hi> (ſaith the Prophet in the III. Pſalme.) All religion begins in feare. And its the end of all things ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi> in the laſt chapter of <hi>Eccleſ. The end of all things</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>is to feare God and keepe his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements.</hi> Yea, its both the beginning and ending, and the continuance of a Chriſtian life; for <hi>worke out your ſaluation in feare and trembling,</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle in the ſecond to the Philippians.) <hi>And bleſſed is the man that fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth alwaies,</hi> Prou. 28.1. <hi>I will teach you</hi> (ſaith <hi>Samuel</hi> in the twelfth chapter of his firſt booke, and the 21. verſe,) <hi>the good and right way. Onely feare the Lord and ſerue him in truth with all your heart, for conſider how great things hee hath done for you.</hi> There is no action therefore, that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds from a Chriſtian through the whole courſe of his life, but ſhould receiue ſuch a tincture from Religion and the feare of God, as ſhould make it remarkeable for a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19136:9"/>godly deede; that if we ſpeake it ſhould be in feare; if we worke it ſhould be in feare; whether we wake or ſleepe or whatſoeuer elſe we doe, all ſhould be done in feare; Nay, the true childe of God takes not ſo much time as to eate his meate without feare. For indeede when as the Lord hath once truely and throughly ſhaken the heart and conſcience of a man, with the terrours of death and hell for ſinne; and hath alſo ſeaſoned his heart with a ſweet apprehenſion and feeling of the comforts of his holy ſpirit; when he hath once as it were giuen him a touch of the ſorrowes of hell, and taſte of the ioyes of heauen: he is euer after fearefull leaſt he againe either incurre the danger of the one, or looſe the happineſſe of the other; As the skinne of that place that is once burned will euer after bee more tender then the reſt. The life of a Chriſtian therefore, is not a life of ſecurity, a life of diſſoluteneſſe and ſenſualitie: but a life of ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, a life of feare, a life of continuall and awfull reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of the preſence and maieſtie of almighty God. Not according to the faſhion of theſe times, wherein men account it a ſmall thing to cozen and deceiue, to extort and opporeſſe, to lie and ſlaunder, to quarrell and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend, to carouſe and reuell, as if there were no God in heauen that doth behold them: The onely cauſe hereof can ſurely be no other then that of the Prophet, in the 36 Pſame. <hi>Non est timor Deiante oculos eorum:</hi> they haue not the feare of God before their eyes. <hi>Primus in orbe Deos fecit timor</hi> (ſaith the heathen Poet,) The firſt thing that euer made men to thinke there was a God was Feare. Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vs that no ſooner nor longer doe we beleeue there is a God then we haue feare. A feareleſſe man therefore is a graceleſſe man; the want of feare being an aſſured and vndoubted teſtimonie, that there is no goodneſſe in him, in aſmuch as it is the firſt grace that is wrought in the heart of a man; and ſo certaine a ground of goodneſſe, that it was generally taken amongſt the Iewes for the whole worſhip of God, and that there can be no part of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19136:10"/>Gods true worſhip where feare is not. As therefore the wants of feare may bee feare vnto vs, if there be any kinde of inclination vnto goodneſſe in vs, vnleſſe we be altogether hardened; ſo alſo if we deſire to be happy, the many promiſes in the Scriptures of diuers and all kinde of bleſſings therevnto, may incourage and moue vs to ſtriue and endeauour our ſelues to ſtand in awe and feare of our gracious God.</p>
            <p>As firſt, Acceptation in his ſight, for <hi>in euery nation</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) <hi>he that feareth God and worketh righteouſneſſe is accepted of him.</hi> Act. 10.35. Secondly Mercy, <hi>for his mercy is on them that feare him throughout all generations.</hi> Luk. 1.50. Thirdly Compaſſion, for <hi>as a Father hath compaſſion on his children, ſo hath the Lord compaſſion on them that feare him.</hi> Pſal. 103.13. Fourthly the continuance of poſteritie, for <hi>bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord, for he ſhall ſee his childrens children, and grace vpon Iſrael.</hi> Pſal. 128.1.6. Fift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly long life, for <hi>the feare of the Lord encreaſeth the daies, and he that is filled therewith ſhall continue and not be viſited with euill. Pro.</hi> 19.23. Sixtly, Riches, Glory and Life, for <hi>the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of humilitie and the feare of God, is riches, glory and life. Prou.</hi> 22.4. Seuenthly, knowledge and illumination in the miſteries of our ſaluation: for <hi>the Lord reueales his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets vnto ſuch as feare him;</hi> and <hi>what man is hee that feares the Lord? him will he teach in the way that he ſhall chooſe. Pſa.</hi> 25 12.14. Eightly, protection and preſeruation. <hi>Behold</hi> (ſaith the Prophet) <hi>the eye of the Lord is vpon ſuch as feare him, to deliuer their ſoules from death, and to preſerue them in time of famine. Pſal.</hi> 33.18. And laſtly, audience vnto our prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, for <hi>to him will I looke</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, and that trembleth at my words. Eſay</hi> 66.2. And in ſumme, all thoſe things that can make vs bleſſed ſhall we be ſure of, if we liue in this feare: for <hi>no good thing doth hee withhold from them that feare him.</hi> As therefore wee doe deſire to be accepted of him; as wee looke for mercie and compaſſion from him; as wee would expect the bleſſings of God vpon our poſterities;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19136:10"/>as we hope for protection and preſeruation from his al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty power; and finally, as we would be made parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of all thoſe bleſſings that may make vs happy, either in this life or the life to come: ſo are wee to endeauour our ſelues at all times to baniſh from our thoughts all ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curitie, and alwaies preſerue in our hearts a reuerent and awfull feare of the dreadfull maieſtie of God; as being aſſured that the diuell will be the accuſer, the Angels the beholders, and the iuſt God the auenger of all thoſe careleſſe and feareleſſe actions, that at any time ſhall proceede from vs, through the whole courſe of our liues.</p>
            <p>Now for the Relatiue part of this feare, that it is a barre and reſtraint vnto ſinne, though reaſon and experience might ſufficiently informe vs herein, yet for our better ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction and encouragement, the Scriptures are expreſſe in many places to this effect.<note place="margin">Pro. 14.17.</note> 
               <hi>The feare of the Lord</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>is a wellſpring of life, to auoide the ſnares of death;</hi> the ſnares of death are the baites of ſinne: the onely preſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue againſt their enticements is the feare of the Lord, ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> The only meanes which the Lord in the time of the Law preſcribed vnto his owne people, to preuent and auoide ſinne: As for example, againſt Oppreſſion, <hi>You ſhall not oppreſſe one another, but thou ſhalt feare thy God, Leuit.</hi> 25.17. And againſt Extortion, <hi>take no vſurie of thy poore brother, nor increaſe, but feare thy God ver.</hi> 36. Againſt Crueltie and Tyranny alſo, <hi>thou ſhalt not rule ouer him with rigour, but ſhall feare thy God. ver.</hi> 43. Againe, <hi>thou ſhalt not curſe the deafe, nor put a ſtumbling blocke before the blinde, but ſhall feare thy God. Leuit.</hi> 19.14. And in the 32. verſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt irreuerence towards ſuperiours, <hi>thou ſhalt riſe vp before the hoarie head, and honour the face of the old man, and feare thy God.</hi> Againſt preſumptuous diſobedience to the Prieſtand Iudges, <hi>And all the people ſhall heare and feare and doe no more preſumptuouſly. Deut.</hi> 17.13. Againſt diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>in ſingleneſſe of heart fearing God. Col.</hi> 3.22. What ſhould I ſtand to inſtance in any more particulars in a
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19136:11"/>matter ſo conſonant and agreeable to common ſenſe, that onely the feare of God doth depart from iniquitie. A point of inſtruction onely ſeruing for a rule to trye whether there be any feare of God in vs or no. For if at any time the diuell, taking aduantage by our owne cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, ſhall ſuggeſt either reuenge for iniuries, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit to get profit; to vſe falſe weights or meaſures to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rich ourſelues, or indirect meanes to attaine our purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; or what wickedneſſe ſo euer ſhall be behooſefull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs: if we feare, we ſhall forbeare. <hi>A wiſe man feareth</hi> (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) <hi>and departeth from euill. Pro.</hi> 14.16. And therefore beloued, to draw an end of this point, in as much as both reaſon doth teach vs, and the Scriptures enioyne vs to ſtand in awe and feare of God; and that thereby we ſhall attaine vnto bleſſings, and eſcape and preuent both ſiune and puniſhment for ſinne: <hi>Let vs then haeue grace whereby we may ſerue God acceptably with reuerence and feare,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 12.28.29.</note> 
               <hi>for euen our God is a conſuming fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo I paſſe from the firſt part of my Text, the <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenſion of ſinne:</hi> vnto the ſecond, the <hi>prohibuion of ſinne,</hi> in theſe words [<hi>Sinne not.</hi>] Wherein I will conſider two things; the duetie enioyned, [<hi>Sinno not;</hi>] and the manner of propoſing it, which is [<hi>indefinitely.</hi>]</p>
            <p>For the firſt, the intent and meaning of the Prophet in theſe words [<hi>ſinne not</hi>] may be both iuſtly doubted of and queſtioned. For in aſmuch as conſidering the fraile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and corruption of our nature: there is a continuall neceſſitie of ſinne in man the Apoſtle witneſſing the ſame of himſelfe, being regenerate in the ſeauenth to the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> that he was <hi>carnall and ſould vnderſinne;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.14.</note> and that of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſa. 19.12.1 Ioh. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>who knoweth how oft he offendeth?</hi> and that of Saint <hi>Iohn, If we ſay we have no ſinne, we deceiue our Ielues, and the truth is not in vs.</hi> How then is it here ſaid, <hi>finne not;</hi> ſwere whereunto, we are to conſider that ſinne in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian man is after a two fold manner; either as a Tyrant; or as a Rebell, As a tyrant before regeneration, when we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19136:11"/>liue as captiues and ſeruants vnder ſinne, obeying it in the luſtes thereof, and yeelindg our members as inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of vnrighteouſneſſe vnto it, without any checke or oppoſition at all. As a Rebell, when as a Chriſtian after regeneration, ſeeles the law of his members rebelling a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the law of his minde, and bringing him againe as an vnwilling captiue, vnto the law of ſinne. Now after this manner, namely, as ſinne is a rebell, there is no man liuing, but ſinne ſhall ſtill continue and remaine with him ſo long as he ſhall liue in the fleſh: which the Lord doth purpoſely ſuffer in his owne elect ſeruants for diuers ends and purpoſes; both to abate the inſulting pride of mans heart, to make them wearie of this world, but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to make good, and ſhew forth his great power in their weakeneſſe. But after the firſt manner; that is, as a Tyrant, ſinne is in no man, that is actually the childe of God, in which reſpect onely, the Prophet in this place doth forbid ſinne, namely, according to the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles exhortation: not, that ſinne be not in you; but that it raigne not in you, that you ſhould willingly obey it in the luſts thereof.</p>
            <p>Which kindes of ſinning Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> differenceth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, comprehending the one vnder name of ſinning ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, and the other of committing ſinne, by <hi>peccare</hi> and <hi>peccatum facere:</hi> In the firſt reſpect (ſaith he) <hi>he that ſaith he hath not ſinne is a lyer and the truth is not in him:</hi> Concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the other, he ſaith, <hi>he that is borne of God ſinneth not:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.9.</note> Theſe commit not ſinne, namely, as a ſeruant of ſinne: Yea he addeth, that he cannot ſinne, to wit, with a full ſwing and conſent of his will, as thoſe that be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwing and conſent of his will, as thoſe that be the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants of ſinne, becauſe the <hi>ſeede of God remaines in him,</hi> whereby he is partly ſpirit, and not onely fleſh: ſo that as he cannot perfectly will that which is good, becauſe of the rebellion of the fleſh; ſo can he not will, with full conſent, that which is euill becauſe of the reluctation of the ſpirit. For howſoeuer <hi>peccare</hi> and <hi>peccatum facere,</hi> to ſinne and to commit ſinne, are not ſo generally differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19136:12"/>but that in many places of the Scriptures, the one is put for the other; yet is there neceſſitie of diſtinction betweene them. For he is ſaid properly <hi>peccatum facere,</hi> to commit ſinne, <hi>qui ſtudio peccanditenetur,</hi> which is ſetled in a delightfull deſire thereof, which bends all the forces of his minde, and the whole ſway of his deſires therevnto. Being a propertie peculiar vnto the reprobate and vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen erate, who (as the Prophet ſaith of them) <hi>inuent miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe vpon their beds,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 36.4.</note> 
               <hi>they cannot ſleepe vnleſſe they haue done euill.</hi> And as the meditation and delight of a true Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſhould be in the law of his God, and in contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereof: ſo is their whole delight and meditation in the law of ſinne, how they may fulfill the luſts thereof: that is, they ſinne <hi>ex animo,</hi> without any reluctation at all; it comes willingly and pleaſingly from them: Their very thoughts and intentions are more damnable, then the ſinfull actions of the godly; why? becauſe they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceede from the heart, their will concurs therewith; and therefore our bleſſed Sauiour ſaith vnto <hi>Iudas, Quod fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sis fac cito,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 13.27.</note> that thou doeſt doe ſpeedily. Hee had then done nothing, yet ſaith our Sauiour <hi>Zuod facis,</hi> What thou doeſt, becauſe his minde was at that time intent and ſet vpon it. Whereas on the other ſide we reade of diuers in the Scriptures, who although they did not exactly ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fill the law and commandements of God in act; yet their thoughts, their affections and their wils, being with and vpon them, they are ſaid to haue kept them. So we reade of the Prophet,<note place="margin">Pſ. 119.121.168.</note> 
               <hi>Feci iudicium &amp; inſtitiam,</hi> I haue done righteouſly and iuſtly: and <hi>I haue kept thy teſtimonies:</hi> and <hi>I haue not erred from thy precepts.</hi> Now how could be ſay thus of himſelfe, when as it is well knowne he had many times ſinned grieuouſly? Why ſurely, moſt iuſtly, if we conſider his heart and affections, though not if we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider thoſe ſinfull actions which by infirmitie he fell in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: For his minde and his will was alwaies to haue obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed God, and he continually applyed himſelfe that way; the law of God was his meditation day and night. In this
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19136:12"/>reſpect therefore the Prophet doth admoniſh vs that we <hi>ſinne not,</hi> that is, that we commit not ſinne, that our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights be not ſet thereon, that our deſires and our wills concurre not therewith.</p>
            <p>Or elſe thus may be the Prophets meaning in theſe words, <hi>ſinne not:</hi> That originall concupiſcence, that ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bituall cuſtome of ſinne which is within our natures, is a corrupt tree continually ſupullulating &amp; ſprouting out; a filthy fountain, ouer flowing at all times all the faculties of our ſoules. Now, <hi>Stand in awe and ſinne not,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, that is, let the feare of God plucke vp thoſe poyſonfull Sprigs, and ſtop the paſſage of thoſe vnwhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome ſtreames, that the one doe not grow, nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doe not flow beyond the bounds and limits of Gods Law.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Iames</hi> doth excellently ſet forth the gradation of ſinne, of its beginning, proceeding and perfecting, in his firſt Chapter, the 14. and 15. verſes. <hi>Euery man is temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>when he is drawne away of his owne luſt, and is entiſed: Then when luſt hath conceiued, it bringeth forth ſinne, and ſinnewhen it is finiſhed bringeth forth Death.</hi> The origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, and whole progreſſion of ſinne vnto the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is in theſe words expreſſed. For Concupiſcence begets it, the will conceaues it, the act brings it forth, and death finiſheth it. Though concupiſcence therefore would al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies beget it in thee, yet <hi>ſinne not,</hi> ſaith the Prophet; that is, yeeld not vnto its entiſements, and let the feare of God hold thee backe from proſtituting thy holy will vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the vnchaſt allurements thereof. <hi>Stand in awe and ſinne not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly to conclude, if for your better vnderſtanding hereof I may illuſtrate it by an Allegoricall reſemblance, you may imagine the ſoule of man at the firſt to haue bin as the Garden of Eden, the Garden of God; wherein the Lord had ingraſted euery thing that was delightfull in his ſight, and pleaſing vnto his taſt: But when as man had ſo defiled this heauenly Paradiſe with the filthineſſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19136:13"/>and ſtench of ſinne, the Lord left this goodly habitation; and ſince its growne a Wilderneſſe, a poole of Snakes, a Cage of vncleane birds, there nothing but thornes and Brambles, Weedes and Thilſtles growes in the ſame. So that now afore regeneration the ſoule is as the ruines of an olde Garden ouer-growne with weedie and poyſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble hearbs. But when it ſhall pleaſe God to returne vnto his Garden, to dreſſe it, to digge and furrow vp thoſe thorny knots by repentance, and plant it againe by faith, and cauſe it to bring forth fruits of Loue: then will hee againe make it his habitation. yet cannot ſuch a curſed ground as is the ſoule of man be ſo dreſſed, but there will ſtill be leſt a diſpoſition to bring forth weedes, if it be not looked vnto, it will ſtill heere and there ſprout out; and if wee be altogether careleſſe, it will ſoone be ouergrown againe, and quite extinguiſh the grace of God. Now what is the iſſue hereof? Why thus, that if the Lord hauing now ridde this Garden from the weeds of ignorance and ſin, and planted it againe with the graces of his holy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, doe commit it vnto our care and charge to dreſſeit and keepe it ſo, and yet wee againe doe giue eare to the ſubtle baites and enchantments of Satan, and defile it any more with ſin: the ſecond error ſhall be worſe then the firſt. Weed it therfore, and keep it cleane; and if thou doſt diſcouer at any time any vnruly paſſion of impati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in thy ſelfe, or any inordinate deſire of pride, to immitate the fantaſticke and fanaticke faſhions of theſe wanton times, or whatſoeuer irregular affection ſhall ſpring out from that filthy vnholſome fountaine within, plucke it vp. Let the feare of God checke and with-hold it: <hi>Standin awe and ſinne not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that hauing (I thinke) ſufficiently explaned the Prophets meaning; in the ſimple prohibition of ſinne, I will proceed vnto the manner of propoſing it, which is indeſinitely; and that in two reſpects, both in reſpect of the perſons, and alſo in reſpect of the time.</p>
            <p>In reſpect of the perſons, it includes all without excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19136:13"/>comprehending in it, both <hi>ſingula generum,</hi> and <hi>ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nera ſingulorum.</hi> For although it were primarily directed to the enemies of <hi>Dauid</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt: yet now the partition wall being taken away, and being all one ſpiritually, it is to be referred vnto all men, none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, as being naturally the children of wrath, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to Chriſt. As it contains in it <hi>ſingula generum,</hi> there is no man liuing in his particular, that can be exempted by any priuiledge from this inhibition of not ſinning; but euery Chriſtian man is bound to looke to his owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon that he ſinne not, neyther againſt God nor man. As it containes <hi>genera ſingulorum,</hi> it likewiſe bindes euery man in his ſpeciall place and condition to be carefull he ſinne not: for as euery man is to be carefull in his owne particular to obſerue the generall rules of Chriſtianity, that therein hee tranſgreſſe not: ſo are all men to looke principally vnto ſuch dueties as concerne their ſpeciall calling, as they are ſuch and ſuch Chriſtians, eyther Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Magiſtrates, Tradeſ-men, Artificers, or whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, that therein eſpecially they ſinne not. And the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er the place is, the more care and feare ſhould accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him that is in it: eſpecially the Miniſter and the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate; becauſe their negligence and vnfaithfulneſſe are not ſinnes that goe alone, but draw a thouſand after them, and therefore are they incident to as much more puniſhment. For next vnto the wickedneſſe of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill, is the vnfaithfulneſſe of the Miniſter and the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate.</p>
            <p>Secondly, in reſpect of the ſinne, it likewiſe excludes none; but wee are inhibited all manner of ſinne. Now for the kindes of ſinne, it is by diuers men reduced into diuers heads. As there are ſinnes againſt the firſt Table, concerning the ſeruice of God. And there are ſins againſt the ſecond Table, tranſgreſſing our duties towards men. Againe, there are ſins of Omiſſion, and ſinnes of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion. Which diuiſion the Apoſtle makes in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth to the <hi>Romanes:</hi> whereby hee ſaith, <hi>the good that I
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19136:14"/>would, I doe not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 7.15.</note> meaning thereby ſinnes of Omiſſion: but <hi>the euill that I would not doe, that doe I:</hi> intimating thereby ſinnes of Commiſſion. Againe, ſinne is deſcribed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to be eyther mentall, or verball, or actuall. So S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> defineth it. <hi>Peccatum eſt dictum, vel factum, vel cogitatum contra legem Dei.</hi> In fine, how many heads of ſinne ſoeuer there may be (I cannot now ſtand to enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merate) they are all heere forbidden. So that all manner of perſons, of all manner of conditions, whether male or female, rich or poore, bond or free, noble or ignoble, of publique or priuate imployment, whether in Church or Common-wealth; are to auoide all kindes of ſinne, whether of ignorance or of conſcience, of neglect or contempt, of omiſſion or commiſſion, of weakeneſſe or wilfulneſſe, of action or affection, by word or by worke; there is no perſon exempted, nor no ſinne excepted, but by expreſſe iniunction from the Lord of all, all manner of perſons are to forbeare all manner of ſinnes.</p>
            <p>But now (beloued) if wee apply this vnto our ſelues, wee ſhall finde no ſmall difference betweene that which the Lord requires of vs, and that we returne vnto him; betweene our duties what we ſhould doe, and our pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes what we doe; betweene forbearing all ſinne, and forbearing no ſinne. For let any man begin at one end of this city, and goe to the other, and but take ſpeciall no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and diligent ſuruey of the carriages of men, and its a hundred to one, if hee diſcouer not almoſt all kinde of ſinne. As happily in the ſuburbs hee ſhall ſee ſome lur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Adulterer come creeping out of one of the brothels of hell, who through the falſe vnfaithfulneſſe of thoſe that ſhould informe and will not, or the mercileſſe leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of them that ſhould reforme and doe not, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in his filthineſſe, and is hardned in his ſinfull and wicked practiſes. Next of all without perhaps he ſhall ſee many of the ſwiniſh ſonnes of <hi>Bacchus</hi> come reeling out of the ſchooles of drunkenneſſe, breathing and belching out nothing but the froth of Ale; diuelliſh and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:19136:14"/>fearefull blaſphemies, to the euerlaſting ſhame and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of man, to the ſcandall of the holy profeſſion of Chriſtianity, to the certaine corrupting and euill example of others, &amp; to the great diſhonour of almighty God. Goe forward and you may ſee ſwarmes of lazie and idle Drones, the very ſhame of this Land, whoſe profeſſion amongſt our reformed Laitie is not farrevnlike the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified Mendicants in the Romiſh Cleargie, euen wilfull pouertie, deſiring rather to begge or ſteaſe; yea ſtarue, then worke and liue by the comfortable fruites of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt labour,</p>
            <p>Here alſo are not wanting thoſe deſperate Ruffines with whom there is no more then a word and a blow, making no more reckoning of a mans life, then if it were to kill a dogge: <hi>Curſed be their wrath for it is fierce,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 49.7.</note> 
               <hi>and their rage, for it is cruell.</hi> Againe, you may heare meete thoſe fatted Epicures, whoſe eyes ſtand out for fatneſſe, that eate and drinke to ſleepe, and riſe vp to play, one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for faſhion they ſometimes take the Church in their way: ſuch there haue beene, are, and will be vnto the end of the world, and yet doe they take it as a wrong, if they be accounted any whit leſſe religious then others. In euery corner likewiſe a company of damnable Atheiſts, vpon euery triſling occaſion darting out helliſh oathes, which makes our land to mourne; wounds the eares of the very hauens themſelues, and cries loud vnto the high throane of iuſtice for ſpeedy vengeance. Hither likewiſe doth oftentimes reſort, thoſe cruell oppreſſors; that make themſelues gorgeous by the ruins of their poore Tenants: Cloathing themſelues with the fleſh of their poore brethren, how ſure are they to finde the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of <hi>Diues,</hi> that ſo little regard the wants of poore <hi>Lazarus?</hi> And laſtly, (for I cannot ſtay to repeate all par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars) whereas the outward deportment of a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an ſhould be nothing more then a louely repreſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of grace and modeſtie: why now, both men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are generally for the moſt part ſo farre tranſported
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:19136:15"/>beyond themſelues by pride, that they turne Apes and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, dauncing through the ſtreetes, as if they knew not whoſe feete they ſtand on: ſo ridiculouſly, vaine, and ſo ſtrangely witleſſe and phantaſticall are men in theſe times, as that (which almoſt I am aſhamed to ſpeake) they are growne proud of their very iangling of the ſtrappes of their bootes. Good God! what mans wit is able to ſinke the depth of thoſe ridiculous follies wherein to vaine man would plunge himſelfe; if either the ſhame of men did not withhold him, or the ſeueritie of ſtrict lawes reſtraine him, at leaſt-wiſe if the awefull re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and feare of Gods almighty power and preſence did not in ſome meanſure bridle and pull backe the head-ſtrong and violent current of his irregular deſires? And in fine, you may here ſee the ſeauen deadly ſinnes withall their attendants, driuen all along before the Diuelto their euerlaſting confuſion: So that Satan marcheth with his helliſh troupes through the Church of God without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troule; and the enemie flouriſheth his coulours amidſt our forces, and yet there is none that riſeth vp againſt him. Surely the Prophet in this place doth enioyne all men of all conditions, in what they are able, to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to ſtoppe and ſtay the paſſages of ſinne. The pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate therefore ſhould endeauour by ſuch meanes as are in their power, by holy prayers and brotherly admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Miniſter by diſcouering vnto men their ſinnes and reprouing their tranſgreſſions. Indeede, this, none of vs can ſay, but for the moſt part its faithfully diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charged: but Reaſon (ſaith one) is a good Orator when it hath force to backe it, and therefore in the third place without the diligence and faithfulneſſe of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate all that we can ſay will little auaile. Now the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of euery ciuill Magniſtrate euen ſuch as know not God, is to looke to the markets and to heare and redreſſe the complaints of all diſturbances of the ciuill peace: but of a Chriſtian Magiſtrate, to ſee that God be not blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and diſhonoured, that Religion be not diſhartned
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19136:15"/>nor diſgraced, but that with all his might hee doe oppoſe and diſcountenance, euen all ſuſpicions of prophaneneſſe and diſhonour vnto God; and as farre as his authoritie will extend, ſeuerely to puniſh all offenders in that kinde, that as he beares not the ſword for nought, ſo being the Miniſter of God, hee may be a reuenger, to execute wrath vpon all that doe euill. <hi>Romanes</hi> 13.4. But now its growne to ſuch a paſſe, that if a man haue riſen to any place of reſpect in this Citie, hee groweth after a manner incontrouleable; hee may ſweare and blaſpheme, hee may ſlaunder or oppreſſe the poore by foreſtalling the Markets, he may oppoſe the Prieſtly office of Chriſt in the power of the keyes, hee may reuell, be drunke, or commit any diſorder when hee will, and his Worſhip ſhall ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him from incurring any danger of puniſhment. But alas (beloued) ſhall the poore honours of a Citie priuiledge any man to diſhonour his GOD, and can wee thinke that the angrie eyes of GOD lookes not vpon ſuch courſes as theſe? Surely there will not alwaies be a time of mercie, but at length the Lord will burſt out into vengeance; for though the Lord ſuffer long and much, yet wee reade not that hee ſuffers alwaies, but at length (as the Prophet ſpeakes) <hi>in the day of his fierce anger will hee viſite vs with the roddes of his wrath, and will poure out his furie like fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And howſoeuer ſome men doe thinke this Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to be greatly reformed from what it hath beene; yet if they looke vpon it with a leſſe indulgent eye, they ſhall ſee but little reformation therein; one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the ſame or worſe ſinnes, masked ouer with more plauſible and colourable pretences, that its Gods wonderfull goodneſſe, wee are not as <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah.</hi> When as the beaſtly beze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19136:16"/>ſinne of drunkenneſſe is become the onely ſinewes of good-fellowſhippe; the filthy pollu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Temples of the holy Ghoſt, at the mention whereof the heart of euery true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſhould euen nauſeate and riſe with indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is generally for the moſt part accounted but as a youthfull recreation, and laughed at. When fearefull oathes are become meere phraſes of gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantrie, and the vnbrotherly contentions of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall minded men are conceited to be Religion and Pictie. When as oppreſſion is accounted forecaſt, and frugalitie, and Pride eſteemed as comelineſſe, Lying held as pollicie, Idleneſſe pretended pouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and the voluptuous and immoderate wallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in natures ſuperfluities defended by a pretence of Chriſtian libertie; and all theſe the moſt hate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and abhominable in the eyes of Almighty God of all others, to paſſe and eſcape vnregarded and vnpuniſhed: Surely, O Lord, wee haue iuſt cauſe to admire thy long ſufferance aboue all thy mercies. The Lord for his infinite mercies ſake, by that almighty power by which hee is able to ſubdue all things to his owne will, breake theſe ſtonie hearts of ours, that wee may alwaies ſtand in awe and feare of that dreadfull Maieſtie, that ſo forſaking the crooked waies of ſinne and iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, wee may hold on our courſe in ſuch pathes as are agreeable to his holy will, vntill ſuch time as it ſhall pleaſe him to tranſplant vs from this vale of miſerie, and make vs glorious inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of thoſe ſacred pallaces, where nothing but light and bleſſed immortalitie, no ſhaddow of matter for teares, diſcontentments, feares, or any vncomfortable paſſions to worke vpon; but all ioy, tranquilitie and peace euen for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer doe dwell. Vnto which place the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19136:16"/>Lord in his due time bring vs all, for Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſake; to whom with the Father and his moſt bleſſed and holy Spirit, be Glorie and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, and Dominion, and Power, both now and for euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FJNJS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>PAge</hi> 17 <hi>line</hi> 28. <hi>for,</hi> Theſe commit, <hi>reade</hi> That is, commits. <hi>p.</hi> 20. <hi>l.</hi> 36 <hi>for</hi> timer. ſinne, <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l. vls. for</hi> whereby, <hi>r.</hi> where.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
